[Music]
I'm joined by Cassie J the director of
the red pill movie and Patricia Omar
kochiya who recently put out the rise of
Jordan Peterson and we've done
interviews with with both of you and
recently we put out the interview with
you Patricia and there are a few
comments that talked about the
similarities between both your and
Cassie's films and the reception to the
films that you're both independent
female directors making films about
controversial topics and have had sort
of mixed responses kind of what you
might call a kind of encounter with
council culture and and I also find
there's a lot of similarities like
you're both from quite a liberal
background and I'm really interested in
in in the what the process was of making
those films whether there's any
similarities I know also in the in the
run-up to this you both watched each
other's films again so I'd be really
interested in any kind of thoughts or
reflections that you have on on each
other's work as well and but I might
just ask Cassie if like if I could ask
you a few more a few years since the red
pill movie came out just to recap what
that experience was like and what the
reception was like maybe that see if
there any similarities that Patricia can
pick up on in write of Jordan Peterson
yeah sure well first off thank you for
having me on here David always good to
see you and Patricia it's so nice to
meet you remotely definitely a fan of
your work and approach and a lot of
things that you did that I have a lot of
respect for so we can get into that in
this conversation but if people are
thinking oh where's Cass I've been for a
while I've been declining all interviews
this year pretty much except for one
back in February but I've been laying
low working on a new project so that's
where I've been but my film the red pill
came out let's see it was released in
theaters October 7th 2018
sixteen and the reason I say the date is
because I think it was just one week
over week and a half after Jordan
Peterson released his professor against
political correctness video which is
kind of one skyrocketed him into the
mainstream so for that reason I think my
experience of watching the rise of
Jordan Peterson was really interesting
because it was the same timeframe of
when I was starting to get out to the
out in the public with the red pill
movie and Jordan Peterson was as well
and so I could really relate to him in
the rise of Jordan Peterson as far as
the blowback that he received and now
unfortunately I can also relate to
Patricia's experience with blowback but
I do think that we have a ton of
similarities with her documentaries as
far as you know I'm Sur the red pill is
certainly more closely related to the
rise of Jordan Peterson than it is to
you know something about environmental
issues or a million different
documentaries that are out there with
that said I think we also have a lot of
differences within our documentaries
which is great because I love to see the
various ways that documentaries can be
made one main difference is that the red
pill movie was a first-person account of
my story I included myself in the film
through video diaries and it was one of
the last decisions I made and making the
film was to include my own journey of
making the film so it's kind of a film
within a film or a story within a story
I was making a movie about the men's
rights activists the men's rights
movement and then I also happen to be
documenting my experience as the
filmmaker making the movie and I
combined the two to make the red pill
movie where as Patricia took a I guess
what would be called a cinema vert a
approach which is a fly on the wall you
don't know who the filmmaker is behind
the camera and it's this very
intellectual you know kind of you feel
like you're sneaking in on private
conversations and it's just a glimpse
into the private life with Jordan
Peterson which is I think the perfect
approach for that story
so yeah we can get more into the details
but I really enjoyed your film dish'
thank you
Patricia would you like to sort of pick
up did you do you do resonate with that
I mean you you've you've quite more
recently had some sort of cinema saying
that they won't show it and and did you
actually have protests or was it most it
was mostly the staff and the cinemas
that said that they weren't comfortable
screening it we didn't have any protests
but yes we had three cancellations and
we had we had several knows that are not
the the typical kind of knows that you
get in the industry when you're
approaching theaters so we hired a very
experienced Booker who's very
well-connected in the industry to
cinemas and and he just commented on how
this wasn't what was typical because no
is the expected response in this
industry but but this was something
different and it definitely seemed like
there was more of an ideological reason
behind some of the knows that we were
getting some theaters were more Frank
than others like there was one theater
that said to us something to the effect
of we think this film is interesting and
fair but we don't want to contribute in
any way to the the cult of Jordan
Peterson something to that effect but I
at least respect the fact that that
theater was honest versus you know some
theaters that said things like well
there's no market viability for this
film and it's a film about Jordan
Peterson who sold over 3 million books
around the world so it's hard to buy
that argument and something interesting
that's happening now is I'm actually
having a conversation with a theatre
that rejected our film and I'm having a
conversation through the letter wiki
platform and this is a theatre that's
three hours away from Toronto so it's in
a smaller town and I really respect the
fact that the cinema owner is willing to
engage and talk about this and it sounds
like she felt a bit unsettled about the
decision that she made but also felt
like she was kind of between a
in a hard place of not wanting to
compromise her values of freedom
expression and conversation as a former
librarian yet at the same time she was
nervous about the kind of pushback she
would get from people in her own social
circle if she were to screen the film
and how it might affect patreon existing
patrons and the reputation of the
theater and she actually mentioned your
film and I just I want to find exactly
what she said about it because she was
mentioning any other instances she had
where she's rejected showing films and
I'm just kind of scrolling through here
oh yes she said the only other film
either than the rise of Jordan Peterson
that I've refrained from showing because
I perceived and dreaded potential
controversy was the men's rights doc the
red pill in 2016
oh well well I guess we are in the same
camp in you seen the red pill Trisha
yeah it has been a while since I watched
I wanted to rewatch it for this
interview didn't have the chance um well
when I first heard about the film it was
in the early stages of this whole
controversy unraveling with Jordan and
so I remember being really curious about
you and being really curious about the
film and I got to see it at the
University of Toronto and it was
interesting to see some footage in the
film at U of T of some of the protests
there I believe it was when Pharaoh was
doing his top they're taken so so it's a
it definitely shed a lot of light on the
the context of of what was happening and
I guess I guess I've never really
identified as a feminist myself but I
wasn't anti-feminist either was just not
not something I associated with my
personal identity about I guess I would
say but through the process of making
this film it's made me kind of think
about it more and I mean there are
things about feminism that I'm grateful
for my guess is I guess I probably would
most align somewhat with fur
wave feminism in the sense that I am
grateful for the women that fought for
female agency so but I'm kind of
diverging so anyway it just it was one
of the things that got me thinking more
deeply about topics that I never really
thought about well do I identify as this
so I found your journey with that and
with investigating it interesting and I
felt like the way the film ended if I
remember correctly that's when you say
that you dropped the label feminist and
I was I I felt kind of a sense like the
story was unfinished in a way at least
your personal story with it in the sense
of you're still maybe kind of figuring
out where you stand with it all because
you were really surprised with what you
found and I know that when I watched
your interview with David one of the I
guess criticisms that you've gone with
the film was the feminists that you had
interviewed in the film when you
mentioned how a lot of people tend to
remember big red as if that's the only
certain even if that's their name or red
maybe not
people tend to remember her the most as
if that's the only feminist you
interviewed but she isn't the only
feminist that you interviewed but I know
that one of my impressions when I first
saw the film was I was curious why there
weren't people like Christina Hoff
Sommers or you know feminists that have
more no one to use that wouldn't
necessarily be completely shutting down
men's rights or the fact that obviously
there are issues that men face too but
you did speak to that a little bit in
your last conversation with David as
well as and I can appreciate it as a
filmmaker that like there's only so much
you can fit in the film and you know
what every Q&A I get asked well why
didn't you include some Harris and why
didn't you include Jordan's five
lecturers and so I get that as well but
I guess um the the point I'm trying to
make is it just it left me a little bit
curious of like where where did you go
after in terms of your own journey and
your own views with it because in the
the film is about the men's rights win
but then it's all
about your journey through that and how
it affected how you feel about feminism
at least as you knew it so I guess it
just left me curious whether there was
kind of more evolution from there or for
how you feel about some of the more
nuanced views about feminism and again
I've I've never been terribly active in
feminist circles and certainly not in
the way that you have so you know you
you have a more tangible experience of
what what it means to you know have that
identity and be active with it as well
so yeah that's I guess the kind of
question that it left me with thank you
I really appreciate you giving it a
thorough reaction to the film I hadn't
seen the red pill in probably two years
at least since now but then I watched it
a couple weeks ago because it just for
the first time became free on YouTube
with ads so I was like no I'm just gonna
play in the background see what I
thought and I was actually very shocked
at how it felt feeling like a new viewer
for the for the first time because you
know you film for so many years and then
you edit and then you see a million of
the screening yeah and it's really like
I mean you can replay it in your dreams
like you know it like to back your hand
and so I had this long period pass where
I hadn't seen it and then I watched it I
guess maybe a month ago and and I did
think like that last line I no longer
call myself a feminist was like this
bomb dropped and then just kind of like
dropped the bomb and then run away and
like you didn't explain why and I was
thinking wow that's that is intense I
could see why that really kind of merged
people or made them stand up and cheer
like their there were you know standing
ovations at that line but yeah I think
you know just in the process of making
it I knew that I was starting my story
explaining that I've you know been a
feminist my entire life and you know my
work has been revolving or revolved
around women's issues and so I open with
that as my identity it is
I can see how you would feel like it was
unfinished not explaining why I just say
I no longer call myself a feminist and
not the film itself but more just it
felt like it was like the end of the
film but the start of your own kind of
transformation or journey like
unfinished in that yeah and and all you
know it's a very quick answer all the
that I've told people when they ask well
why don't you call yourself a feminist I
I've dropped all labels I mean it unless
it's something that is actually like an
identifying part of you whether say
you're gay or you're Christian or you're
Republican those are you know I think
those are labels that help communicate
in a shorthand manner how you identify
politically or religiously or your
sexual orientation but to say feminist
it's not I think I really do think that
the problem is everyone's definition of
feminism is different so to tell someone
you're feminist that is not actually
communicating with them your views
because you don't know what their
definition is and what's really
interesting as well is having having
interviewed both of you and spent a
little bit of time with both of you
there's a lot of suspicion in this area
of covering these controversial topics
in a sort of either a sensationalist way
or a kind of bad faith way or but the
impression I get from both of you and I
remember it was after I spoke to Warren
Farrell and Cassie that the fact that
you're in the film so much I had not
suspicions but I did I did wonder like
how much of your journey was genuine and
how much of it was was for the Cameron
for the narrative and talking to Warren
I realized no you've really gone in and
as a feminist wanting to know more about
it and have your mind changed by the
experience and I know Patricia you are
actually covering Jordan Pederson the
you are completely blindsided by the
fact that the professor grants political
correctness videos came out because you
were covering for the sort of Jungian
perspective and so you
kind of went in with a real I'm like I'm
convinced that you both went in not
wanting to kind of do a sensationalist
film or in any way kind of exploiting
the material it was very much in a sort
of wanting to know like a really good
faith attitude um and that's a
similarity I think that both both of you
have right right I guess in both
instances we were surprised with what we
what where the films took us I guess you
could say definitely and we set out and
from what I've read about your story
Patricia we both set out with a
different film in mind but then had to
share the truth of what had actually
unraveled while we were filming yeah
it's something also something that I
really appreciate about your film is how
much airtime you gave to critics of
Jordan Peterson and you know a lot of
people with my film have wondered oh is
she a men's rights activist was this a
propaganda piece was it funded by men's
rights activists and all that I would
say is no it was those assertions are
not true um but you know there is a lot
of speculation about the agenda of the
filmmaker and I I would think that
someone that is really trying to be
balanced and give give props to to both
sides and both arguments for the
audience to come to their own conclusion
would give airtime to the critics of
whatever you're following whether it be
joined Peterson or men's rights activist
so but now you know three years after
the film's release I a little part of me
wonders was that the right decision
because it didn't seem to matter in the
end with the mainstream media smearing
my name in the film and saying that it
was propaganda or whatever else so
including feminist
academics and feminist professionals
critiquing the men's rights movement
within my film didn't seem to to help
with the image of my film as being
balanced so then I wonder well I could
have taken that maybe 40 minutes within
my two-hour film
actually gone into many of the other
men's rights issues that I wasn't able
to include because the time constraints
things like false allegations or suicide
rates or sentencing disparity etc so my
question for you Patricia's was it hard
for you to include so much airtime to
the trans activists and to the critics
of Jordan Peterson like his friends
Bernard and will rather than using that
time to go more into Jordan's ideas and
writings and teachings
mm-hmm in my case no it wasn't difficult
to include those those voices in the
film and I think for the kind of film I
was trying to make it was integral to it
because a lot of my film was about the
polarized nature of this topic and how
Jordan Peterson himself in his public
persona became so polarized and if
anyone watching has seen our poster you
see Jordan portrayed as this kind of
mythological figure with with this
divide on both sides of people
approaching him as a kind of Messiah or
as a devil but then the film itself
reveals him as vulnerable human being so
in order to make a film about that I
think it was really integral to include
those voices and I know and so I don't
think even though I know what you mean
in that you know even with our film it's
like we we worked really hard to show
the nuance and to to kind of build a
comprehensive understanding of this from
different perspectives but you know we
still had some cancellations and whatnot
but at the end of the day I think the
most important thing is the integrity of
the film itself and you know regardless
of how you know people are going to
perceive it and you can never really
please everyone unfortunately but I mean
I know that when we had test screenings
in our living room and when we brought
in people from different perspectives
and we had you know everyone from
diehard and peterson fans people whose
lives have been changed from george
two self-proclaimed Marxists and
feminists LGBTQ people people who
haven't heard of Jordan Peterson and
when we had them all in our living room
and we were in this space where people
could have genuine conversations I feel
like the kind of transcendence of the
culture war that we were trying to
achieve I feel like in our living room
it happened but of course in theaters
and and you know through the eyes of the
media it's it's much harder to achieve
that so so I think it was really
important to include those other voices
and I would say I wrote a bit about this
maybe it was in the area article I don't
remember where but a lot of people use
the word balanced to describe the rise
of Jordan Peterson and and I get it and
it kind of it makes sense as a shorthand
but balance isn't actually what I was
trying to Dallas isn't really what I was
trying to achieve because there can be a
superficiality to balance you know will
include like X percentage of air time to
the opposition and and whatever it is
but it was more so about creating a
journey in the film that was kind of a
roller coaster ride because that's what
it was like for me witnessing all of
this unraveling and I think the truth is
complicated and the truth is nuanced
most of the time and it certainly was
the case for witnessing this story so
those those aspects were necessary in
order to paint that really full and
complex picture and to send people on
that journey and sometimes make people
uncomfortable and there have been you
know the art criticism from people who
have said something like well you know
this film is it's unfortunate that this
film could have been used as more of a
tool to make people like Jordan Peterson
more and to kind of convert them into
followers and I think that's propaganda
and that's not what I was interested in
making and the irony is that
it's not what Jordan Peterson's at the
heart of his philosophy that's not what
he's about either so there's an irony
there for people who are remark about
way that's what I've got a slightly
mischievous question that just came to
me there's some suspicion in this area
of using this controversy to help sell
these films so do you and I wouldn't
necessarily say that that's a bad thing
like Jordan Peterson said on the Joe
Rogan show that he's learned to monetize
social justice warriors that actually
the more that people scream about it if
you've got a good product then actually
it helps the the marketing do you think
it's helped in any way would you say
that you'd ever you've ever played to
that either of you I would say or are it
helped in some ways and it's heard it in
others and we're very well aware of both
and we knew that so you know our film
the premiere happened in Toronto
September 26 of this year and it was
right around that time I don't remember
who was before or after that the news
came out about the Carleton Theatre in
Toronto cancelling our week-long run
that was scheduled for right after that
premiere and you know I knew there were
a lot of risks involved with this story
being public and being interviewed about
it but at the same time I also thought
you know it deserved to be public if you
know people are asking about it I'm
going to answer questions about it so
obviously there are the ways that it
helped the film is you know when when
something gets canceled people want to
know well what is it what's so bad about
it why I get it arouses curiosity and
it's natural that's human nature and it
also made more media outlets interested
in their story I frankly wish that more
of them we're interested in reviewing
the film but most of them were
interested in the story of a
cancellation so there's that side of it
but then the ways that I would say it
hurt the film is because the story
that's being reported on is the
cancellations it's or
starts to put you in the same box of
perception of okay well so you're that
we got accused of adopting the same
narrative as Jordan Peterson with with
regards to cancellations
and it's interesting we were just doing
an interview about this yesterday and we
were talking about how there's something
so ironically kind of postmodern about
dismissing the reality of what's
happening as simply a narrative and so
that actually heightens Jordan
Peterson's argument and I understand
where that criticism comes from because
there is this benefit to you know
gaining more attention when
cancellations are happening and you know
we acknowledge that but at the same time
then we're sort of put in this box we're
accused of things like that and you know
there's certain media outlets that then
become more interested in covering the
story than others and so it's it's the
more conservative media outlets so you
know we when we're trying to try and
send a culture where it's very difficult
to navigate a media space that you know
where you're immediately going to be put
into a certain box and the other
negative thing about that cancellation
is that I mean the it's difficulty I say
we face is that I I really wish that our
film could have gotten more screenings
in mainstream and art house theaters and
a lot of those theaters look to the
major markets like Toronto in New York
and when we had that cancellation in
Toronto a lot of all the surrounding
theatres said okay so I'm not gonna
touch that and we knew that was
happening but now through this
conversation I'm having in the letter
wiki platform this theater owner
admitted that that happened in her case
so it's very kind of trying to actually
have something to point to that's
concrete evidence of what we knew was
happening so in some ways it helps in
some ways it hurts I guess I would say
mmm-hmm yeah I definitely agree on a lot
of those points and it is ironic how the
reactions to our films really do go to
support the the topics discussed in the
films even more you know within my film
we talk about the silencing of these
ideas in here the film was being pulled
from
many theaters the most common protest t
platforming kind of experience for the
red pill was actually being accepted
into theaters and then either feminist
activist or probably extremist activist
usually would protest the theater and
send threats and and then sometimes also
board members going against the theater
owner saying that you need to pull the
film so so oftentimes it was a booked
screening that was then removed which is
why i think that's the perfect example
of an attack on freedom of speech and
and you know a censorship kind of you
know a form of censorship as if it's a
book in a library that's now being
pulled and burned so cuz some people
said that it oh it's not censorship
because you don't get to screen your
film in this theater well we were going
to screen the film in the theater and
people paid to watch it in the theater
and then it was removed so um but it
yeah what was the question again
remember
was there any temptation to play up to
that narrative I'm being silenced and
and did you maybe play up to it a little
a little bit I actually did not and you
know people can believe me or not it I
don't know how else how many different
ways to say the truth and and have
people actually believe in it because it
just doesn't work apparently
but yeah I did not play into it we had
no publicity you know machine or group
of people sitting around a round table
or even myself sitting at a table alone
pondering okay how can I get this film
banned or censored or get people riled
up and and I certainly know that happens
because you know I've seen it within
feminist communities and men's rights
communities where they are trying to
think of ways to shocked and appalled or
you know good attention you know like
what's free the nipple you know that
that's the way to get printed in the
media and and you know this shock value
and then the men's rights activists also
do a lot of things that can can get you
know negative media attention but they
think alright any attention
good attention so I really didn't stoke
any kind of controversy fire I mean
except for making my film but I don't
think that was set out to stoke the
controversy I was trying to share what I
learned but you know I I honestly I was
perfectly content if the film just you
know fell on deaths ears but but I sorry
deaths deaths ears but I knew that you
know this is the journey I went on the
this is the best representation of the
people I interviewed and and this you
know it's just two men to start
conversations but say it never really
got out in the world and it just you
know collected dust I I would still
sleep okay at night so the protests and
the controversy for me it was actually
just a big pain you know I I think it's
definitely a double-edged sword which is
what Patricia I think was talking about
where yeah it's great that more people
are hearing about it because of the
controversy and maybe going to see it
because they want to see what is this
film that's banned mmm but then also a
lot of people have actively not seen my
film because they've just chosen to be
on the side that we're gonna be against
this film and we need to unite and stay
together and I don't even want to watch
it I don't want the filmmaker to get you
know any of my views on Amazon Prime or
you know pay for a rental or whatever on
iTunes so they I mean I've brought up
the film the red pill at different
parties and people not knowing I was the
filmmaker and they would just roll their
eyes and go all that trash and I'm like
oh did you see it and they're like no
the filmmaker but so it is a double
edged sword and you know in an ideal
world the film would've gone to Sundance
or South by Southwest and done the kind
of proper indie way of getting into the
mainstream of getting accolades and
recognition from your community of
fellow filmmakers and you know people in
the industry that that respect the way
cinema is made but we didn't have that
option you know
submitted to festivals and you know I
applied for grants we never raised
funding through that way which is why I
did the Kickstarter campaign and so yeah
I mean I guess to categorize it in my
head I guess the way to make it as an
indie filmmaker now is to either be
accepted by the mainstream and get into
the big film festivals or immediately
get great distribution and just I think
you know that's the easier way I mean as
far as the opposite option is you get
declined from all the mainstream that
the mainstream media really tries to
smear in every different way and really
the only way to get out to the public is
to how that Venus talked about whether
it be on the forums online or just word
of mouth and people being shy about
sharing it because they don't know you
know what side you're on and it becomes
like this nefarious or like you know
secretive kind of movement and that
ended up being the case with the red
pill but yeah I certainly didn't I
didn't seek it out and I mean this is
something Patricia was hinting at before
about that we're in an environment where
a loss of things are you could say
weaponized that that certain topics or
immediately sort of drawn into this sort
of culture war dynamic that everyone
kind of assumes that you're on one side
or the other how's that being for you
both like covering something that's been
this polarizing what's the experience
beams it being at all kind of
eye-opening or radicalizing or how has
it shifted your perspectives it's been
well it's been challenging it's opened
my eyes to a lot of things and there's
there's a lot more like politically that
I've come to learn and also to question
and myself and kind of shake out some
beliefs that were more superficial but
also it's also something that was just
coming to mind with this is I would say
that we also experience some of this
kind of pushback on the right is well so
for example
I mean because we we sort of give up on
mainstream in our house cinemas at some
point we were looking to schedule
screenings at churches and with local
groups and Jordan Peters and meetup
groups and just see you know what will
venues we could rent out and that's how
we built our North American tour and at
one point we were talking with
turning-point and they basically
explicitly alluded to the fact that they
were interested in seeing whether there
were parts of the film that they could
use for the next election and I was glad
that once they saw the film which which
you know I I was very a gangsta now
because I'm not interested in the film
be used as a propaganda tool but I was
glad that once they saw the film we
never got a call back and then okay
we're doing something right here and so
it just happens to be that the left and
the progressives those are the people
that are running the art house and
mainstream cinemas because most of the
artists tend to be on the left and so I
think this phenomenon very much exists
on the other side too it's just that
those aren't the people typically that
are running the cinemas and there have
been a couple of cinemas that after
hearing about the cancellations they
contacted us and said we'll screen your
film at our cinema and you know it
tended to be the like Trump supporters
I'm more conservative my goal people
that we're running those cinemas that
approached us I don't know if I entered
your question though so as far as I
understand the question David you're
asking with this polarization around our
films how we kind of landed right on the
on the field is that right yeah yeah
what's the impact being on you
personally I know I remember from from
our interview before I think Warren
Farrell said you enter him to ask how am
I gonna lose lots of my friends and
hoping that he would kind of put your
mind at rest if he said yes so yeah just
how is it being making
about something this topical but this
polarizing mm-hmm
yeah actually many of my interviews
warned me that if I tell the truth I
will be essentially burned at the stake
for it and Warren Farrell did tell me
that I don't know if he told me while
we're filming maybe after the film was
released but he said you will lose a lot
of your friends and so I started asking
him about what he experienced and this
was one of the few times that I saw
Warren break down crying I hope that's
okay to say that but but yeah he because
he was so involved in feminism through
you know the late 60s 70s and Beyond and
then and then really started digging
into men's issues and and you know
adding okay I'm my family says I'm the
queen about it analogies and I thought
of this new about analogy that helps
explain what the red pill was trying to
do I think what Warren Ferrell's work
tries to do which is imagine this jar
and there's pennies being put in the jar
and you know feminists are so long have
been saying oh you know we've got human
sex trafficking and we have maturity
issues and we have you know sexual
assaults and all these things and keep
putting incense and Warren Farrell and
other other academics or if you want to
call them activists are trying to bring
men's issues to this discussion and try
to throw their two cents in literally
and you know everyone else in the gender
political world is throwing it out
saying your since they're not allowed in
this jar so it's not it's not there that
the red pill is trying to say oh this is
actually the way you know that the world
works that women have the power and that
men are the only oppressed gender the
only gender that has issues not that at
all it's just adding the two cents to an
already very vast amount of films and
books and podcasts and whatever else
about feminist issues or trans issues or
whatever else so the reason I have to
say that is because I still do have a
lot of of my feminist friends that has
remained my friend and they would even
say despite the red pill
but you know they have hang-ups that
that they're thinking that I'm
discounting women's issues or or all
these other things and so I'm just
trying to illustrate that it's just
adding to the discussion and
unfortunately that's the source spot
right now at least in the last few years
probably a lot longer than the last few
years but at least with the release of
the red pill I've really seen that
that's the area that you're not allowed
to speak up and you know I at first so
talking about the polarization I also
want to add that you can't choose your
fans and that's something that has been
difficult for me is that there are a lot
of people who've I'm gonna say a lot
it's definitely a my very small
percentage of all the fans of the red
pill but there is a small percentage of
people who I would not align with and I
would not want them representing the
film or sharing with people and you know
them being the spokesperson for it but
nevertheless they they are fans of the
film and they're trying to get it out in
the world and and it is it is a weird
thing that I've had to I guess accept is
you can't pick your fans and you know I
it sounds like Patricia's liberal or at
least was at some point I I've been
progressive liberal most of my life and
then the last few years I would say I'm
more Center but I'm definitely not right
and and we do have a lot of supporters
on the right and because the film is
released a month before Trump was
elected then you know it came out at
this highly polarized time and a lot of
people who attended our film screenings
had the maggots on and I had a feminist
friend of mine a longtime friend of mine
who went to a screening of the film in
Denver Colorado and she she was and I
don't use this word facetiously but she
was triggered by seeing so many maggot
hats in the theater and she had to walk
outside
collect herself before the film started
because just seeing that angered her and
long story short she went to the film
with her boyfriend and that night they
ended up breaking up because of their
differing views on the film so you know
I hate hearing stories like that because
I don't want to think that the film is
dividing people in that way but I have
also heard so many more stories of the
film uniting partners and allowing
husbands or sons or Father's to open up
about their difficulties and have you
know how their stories fall on receptive
ears and so it's been hard but I do hope
that our films will stand the test of
time and that they can be looked back on
you know 20-plus years from now and just
be an example of not only the content of
the film but also their reactions to the
film making a statement about the
culture we live in today and so in that
way I think our films have many layers
of lessons and you know kind of having
your finger on the pulse of society to
see how they react right now I'd love to
ask you both what we've got coming up
next what your your next projects I
guess Patricia you're probably still in
the middle of promoting rise of Jordan
Peterson but have you given any thought
about what you're gonna be doing next
definitely so the the next big project I
wanted to tackles I want to go back to
the original film that I was making
about Jordan and his friendship with
indigenous Carver Charles Joseph and I
think we may have talked about this in
our previous interview I don't remember
how in-depth we went into it but the
initial story that I was making for a
year and a half before Jordan released
those videos was about how Charles
Joseph who's from the quak quak quak
nation he lives in the west coast of
Canada Charles's family was adopting
Jordan into their family and the reason
for that was because of the significance
of the artwork that Charles was giving
to making for Jordan there's there's a
protocol that has to
be followed and it's not just a matter
of buying art it's theirs they're sacred
things that are in their sacred
symbology and stories that are in this
artwork and so there's a responsibility
that comes with that and so Jordan is
now his brother and so I was filming
sacred ceremonies that were taking place
and also the renovations at majora team
was doing to his home he was adding the
third floor modeled after an indigenous
longhouse and it was filled with
Charles's artwork so for a year and a
half I was making a film about that and
that's what I intend on going back and
finishing now that we've just wrapped up
our tour we stopped planning some
screenings and we will be planning a
small tour in Asia in the spring in
March but yeah that's that's what I'll
be tackling next and the film is
tentatively called Mahalo which in
Quaqua l'm just Charles's language means
to dream and kasi you said you've been
hibernating for a while well I'm working
on a new feature now I'm very excited
about it we'll be filming all throughout
2020 and so the red pill was my third
feature documentary the first was called
daddy I do and it was about women's
issues the second was the right to love
and it was about LGBTQ issues and you
know the red pill was about the men's
rights movement so I've definitely been
you know gender politics has been my
wheelhouse but this film is the first
time really kind of stepping out of that
although gender politics is a huge topic
I would say this new film is even bigger
and more widespread so just I guess a
little teaser I won't go into the whole
thing but this film will be looking into
trauma and something that I've really
learned from all my previous work is
that trauma does not discriminate it's
across all genders all socio-economic
statuses all races all ages and so you
know I've seen I've been filmmaking for
well since 2008 and I've seen and heard
so many heartbreaking stories and it
seems like it's actually a seems like
everyone
drama and they're in their past or
something that they're eventually going
to face that's difficult and so this
film aims to to look at how we can heal
a lot of these wounds and yeah so I'm
really excited about it and I'll be
filming all of 2020 rebel wisdom is a
new sense making platform bringing
together the most rebellious and
inspiring thinkers from around the world
if you're enjoying our content then you
can help us make more by becoming a
subscriber which will give you access to
a load of exclusive films also you can
then join our group zoom calls to
discuss the ideas in the films and you
can send us ideas for questions for
upcoming interviews and if you're a
regular viewer you'll know we talked a
lot about the value of embodying or
actually living out the ideas that we
talked about so that's why we run
regular events in London check out the
links on the website for more and hope
to see you soon
you